chapter 5.
As each day passed I would learn, in our
talk,
something about the little prince's
planet, his departure from it and about
his journey.
The information would come very slowly
following the course of the little
Prince's thoughts.
It was in this way that I heard, on the
third day,
about the catastrophe of the baobabs.
This time, once again I had the sheep to
thank for it.
For suddenly the little prince asked me
as if seized by a grave doubt--
"It is true is it not
the sheep eat little bushes?"
"Yes, that is true
I'm glad!"
I did not understand why it was so
important that sheep should eat little
bushes.
But the little prince added:
"Then it follows that they also eat
baobabs?"
I pointed out to the little prince that
baobabs were not little bushes, but, on
the contrary, trees as tall as castles;
and that even if he took a whole herd of
elephants with him, the herd would not be
able to eat up one single baobab.
The Little Prince laughed at the idea of
a herd of elephants
We would have to put them up on top of
one another
he said.
But he made a wise comment:
"Before they grow so big
baobabs start out by being little."
"That is so very true I said.
"But why do you want the sheep to eat the
small baobabs?"
He answered me at once
um
as if he was speaking of something that
was self-evident.
And I was obliged to make a great mental
effort to solve this problem, without any
assistance.
Indeed, as I learned,
there were on the little Prince's Planet
as on all planets--
good plants and bad plants.
In consequence, there were good seeds
coming from good plants, and bad seeds
from bad plants.
But seeds are almost invisible.
They sleep deep in the heart of the
earth's darkness, until one of them
suddenly decides to wake up
Then this little seed stretches itself
and begins timidly at first--
to push a charming little sprig
inoffensively upward towards the sun.
If it is only a sprout of radish or a
sprig of rose bush one would let it grow
wherever it might wish.
But when it is a weed or a bad plant, one
must root out and destroy it at once as
soon as it is so recognized
foreign
terrible seeds on the little Prince's
Planet these were the seeds of the
baobab.
The soil of that planet was infested
with them
but if you do not attend to this upper
routing in time you will never get rid
of a Baobab It spreads over the entire
planet
its strong roots bore clear through it
And if the planet is too small, and if
there are too many baobabs the planet
May well split in pieces...
"It is a question of discipline said the
little prince to me later on.
"When you have finished your own toilet
in the morning it is time thereafter to
attend to the planet's toilet just so,
with the greatest care.
You must see to it that you pull out the
baobabs very regularly the moment they
can be distinguished from the rose
bushes they resemble so closely in their
earliest youth.
It is very tedious work," the little
prince added,
"but it is also very easy."
And one day he said to me:
"You ought to make a beautiful drawing, so
that the children where you live can see
exactly how all this is.
That would be very useful to them if
they were to travel someday
it may seem convenient Sometimes to put
off one's work until another day.
But in the case of baobabs it would be
catastrophic to do so
I knew a planet that was inhabited by a
lazy man. He had neglected three little
bushes..."
So, as the little prince described it to
me, I have made a drawing of that planet.
I do not much wish to act like a
moralist. But the danger of baobabs is so
little understood, and the risks are so
considerable to anyone who might get
lost on an asteroid, that for once I am
making an exception to my reserve.
"Children," I say plainly,
"watch out for the baobabs!"
My friends, like myself, have been
skirting this danger for a long time,
without ever knowing it; and so it is for
them that I have worked so hard over
this drawing.
The lesson which I pass on by this means
is worth all the trouble it has cost me.
Perhaps she will ask me,
"Why there are no other drawings in this
book is magnificent and impressive as
the drawing of the baobabs?"
The reply is quite simple.
I have tried.
But with the others I have not been
successful.
When I made the drawings of the baobabs
I was carried beyond myself by the
inspiring force of urgent necessity